<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new dialoge called the endightment agaynste mother Messe</title>
            <title>Endightment agaynste mother Messe</title>
            <author>Punt, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104466</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840204</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4680</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10222)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4680)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 140:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new dialoge called the endightment agaynste mother Messe</title>
                  <title>Endightment agaynste mother Messe</title>
                  <author>Punt, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By VVyllyam Hyll, and Wyllaym Seres, dwelling in Paules Church yeard at the signe of the grene Hyll,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. .M.D.XLVIII. the .xvii. day of decembre.] [1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: W.P. [i.e. William Punt].</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dialogues, English (Middle) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4680:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:4680:1"/>
A new <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>LOGE CALLED THE</hi> EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dightment agaynſte mother Meſſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mathew the vi.</bibl>
               <p>Euery tre that bringeth not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th good frute ſhalbe hewen downe and Caſte in to the fyre. Wherfore by their frutes ye ſhall knowe them</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="quotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:4680:2"/>
            <q>
               <p>FOR What ſo euer ye haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken in darknes, that ſame ſhall be herde In the lyghte, and that which ye haue ſpoken in the eare euen in ſecrete places, ſhalbe prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched Euen on The toppe, of the howſe</p>
               <bibl>Luke the .xii.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>YF ANY man worſhippe the beaſte and hys. Image and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue his marke In hys forhead or on hys Hande the ſame ſhall drynke the wyne of the wrathe of God whyche ys powred In the coppe of his wrath and he punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth In fyre and brymſtone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the holy Angells and before the Lame.</p> 
               <bibl>Iohn reuelacion .xiiii. Chaptre.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="speakers">
            <pb facs="tcp:4680:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>THE NA</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the ſpeakers in this enditment</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>GODES vuord</item>
                  <item>the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Iuge</item>
                  <item>The ouerſeers of hir.</item>
                  <item>Veryte and kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leg hir accuſers</item>
                  <item>Vuiſdom the ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent</item>
                  <item>Daniell the crier</item>
                  <item>The tvuelf Apoſtels panild on a queſt of hir</item>
                  <item>Ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicta dei and final deſperacion mother Meſſe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hir ſurtiſe maſter Couetus.</item>
                  <item>maſter ſtifneck</item>
                  <item>Antipus the layler</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4680:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A NEVVE DIALOGE CALLED</hi> the enditement agaynſt mother meſſe. Verite begynneth,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rother knowledge ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte thou tel me what ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes ys now abrode a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the people con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g godes word. <hi>knovvledg</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther veryte I here no newes but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhal floryſh according to godes wil for eany thing that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue. <hi>Verite.</hi> But as I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de brother knowledge there is ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye people offended wythe it that it ſhold be ſo. <hi>knovledg.</hi> Al though they he offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded brother veryte yet it is but a foly to ſpurne againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prycke. <hi>Verite.</hi> Verylye that ys tru for that that the heauenlye father hathe not plantyd, ſhalbe plucket
<pb facs="tcp:4680:3"/>
vp by the rotes &amp; caſte into hel fire yet they haue no grace but repyne at that thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyl not be. <hi>knovv</hi> What remedy brother verite ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g they wilbe obſtackle agaynſt the truthe. <hi>Verite.</hi> Yes brother know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege ther is remedy it is your part to preache vnto them the veryte with a meke ſpryte &amp; yf eany man be ouer takin of afaute, as ſaynte paul ſaith i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vi. to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> galatheans you which are ſpryttuall informe hym with a meke ſpryt, &amp; conſyder thyne owne ſelfe. That thou be not tempted ſo well as he. <hi>knovv.</hi> brother verite I haue <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ched vnto them the true word of god, as the lorde hath taught yt me, &amp; I haue traueled from contre to contre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moch pai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es &amp; perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for chriſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es name ſake &amp; I haue alſo declared ther abhomynacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; filthy doctri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e vnto them deſyring them gentlye
<pb facs="tcp:4680:4"/>
to leue yt, &amp; cleaue vnto the verite and I hath alſo prayd vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord to open ther blynd hartes, that the tru knowleg of thriſt might enter in, vppon the which brother verite I thanke my lord god, whome I hathe ſeruyd frome my youthe there hath ben ſome that hath for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſakyn ther abhomynacion &amp; hath receyued the veryte of Chryſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wyſſe ther hathe bene other that hath ben ſtyphenecked wythe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtonding the verite w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; murder, oh brother v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rite the lord is mi Iuge, I hathe <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ached on to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwet ꝓmiſe &amp; liuely doctrine of Ieſu chriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as gentyl a ſpryt as hart may think declaring vnto them, ther abhominacion &amp; fylthy doctryne, yet will they be ſtyfenec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked pharyſes ſtyll, but nowe I thank my lord god the ſercher of al ſecretis, that it hath pleaſed hym
<pb facs="tcp:4680:4"/>
to Inflame our noble king w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly ſprite by the whiche he hathe contrary to ther myndes plucked downe the greateſt parte of there abhominable Idolatri intending no leſſe by godes grace, then for to cote it vp al by the harde rotes how be yt brother veryte I wyll ſhow you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is one abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſittith ſore in mens concience that we muſte ſee a remedye for for the Goſpels ſake, which ys the mother of al myſchef<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; the abhomi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Verite,</hi> why bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther knowleg what is hir name ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you tell. <hi>knovledg.</hi> yes truely hir name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s as I vnderſtande mother meſſe a woman that hath brought the people in to a deuely ſhe trade. <hi>Verite.</hi> wher i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what trade hath ſhe brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I prai you tel me <hi>knov.</hi> truly ſhe hath brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4680:5"/>
ſuch a trade that ſhe hath ſet her ſelfe in the ſeare wher the lyuing god of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſit, morouer brother verite ſhe vaunce her ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe to be a god of godes ye an mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re then a god, for where as God is the omnipotent father of heauen and the euerlaſting God without beginning and without endynge the creatour of heauin and earthe &amp; al other thinges wherby he can not create hym ſelfe, yet wyll this blaſphemous mounſter make the people beleaue that ſhe can creat &amp; make god, wher as god can not make him ſelfe for he hath nether beginnyng nor endinge. Alſo bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther veritie ſhe ſayth ſhe can dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer the ſely ſoules that hath bene long pitouſly puniſhed in the pai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of purgatori fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther paines &amp; tormentes, moreouer ſhe ſaithe ſhe can make fayre wether &amp; rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="tcp:4680:5"/>
&amp; heale all ſicknes, &amp; bring da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned ſoles out of hel, alſo ſhe ſaith ſhe can purchaſe remiſſion of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by the offering vp againe of Chriſtes bodi and bloud &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fiue woordes make both god and man wherby ſhe wold make God parciall a lyer &amp; no god which is plain hereſy treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; trayterly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for by her ſaying god ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no god without her help wherby ſhe wold take the crowne and honour from god and ſet it vpon her ſelfe and furthermore ſhe teacheth the people with her filthy doctrine &amp; ſubtil conueyaunce making them beleue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exccepte they do heare &amp; ſe her play in her iuglyng garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and that in the morning eueri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dai thei ſhould not proſper nor go forwarde in their buſines wher a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout they go, alſo wher as I with the doctrine of Ieſus Chryſt had brought
<pb facs="tcp:4680:6"/>
a fewe to the true knowledge. ſhe hath w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hyr fylthy tradicions and wicked laws compellid them with perſecucion and cruelte, to falle from the verite, &amp; to cleaue vnto hir fylthy doctrine, &amp; yf ther were ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that wold not denye Ieſu chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte but ſtycke to hys houlſom doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne they ſhold ſtrayt ways with cruell perſecucion ſuffre deathe, wherfor yt ys tyme ſhe where rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out from the chriſtyance and &amp; reſted of treaſon, thefte and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as ſhe hath deſeruid no leaſſe <hi>Verite,</hi> wel brother knowlege ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g yt is as you haue ſpoken I wold deſyer you to go to my brother wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome the Sarge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring him er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſtly to make a narowe ſerch for hir, &amp; tach hyr of treaſon theft and murder. <hi>knov</hi> brother verite it ſhal not nede for he comith yender my think. <hi>veryte.</hi> truly he doth indede
<pb facs="tcp:4680:6"/>
               <hi>knouv.</hi> what brother wiſdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worde with you I pray. <hi>vviſd.</hi> ſir what is your pleſur y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you wil ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me <hi>knovv</hi> brother wiſdome my brother veryte &amp; I doth ſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de you, to tach mother meſſe of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theft &amp; murder, &amp; lay hir faſt i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> newgat y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe mai be forth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at al times. <hi>vuiſd..</hi> ſir it ſhalbe don by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al mi hart w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as moch ſpede as I may. <hi>Verit.</hi> I praye you brother wiſdom let it be ſo. <hi>Vuiſd.</hi> brother knowleg I pray you where is hir moſt abydi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trade where I maye lay wayte for hir. <hi>Knovu</hi> brother wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir moſt abidi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is at pouls or i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t feithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ꝑiſh vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der pouls church or at ludgate in ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t martens, ꝑiſh &amp; if you chance not of hir there walke vnto ſaint pulckers church and if you loke well you ſhall Fynde hyr In one of thoſe plaſys wytheoute fayle
<pb facs="tcp:4680:7"/>
               <hi>vviſd.</hi> Well brother knowledge ſeing it is your mynd &amp; my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther verytis to gether I will do my dyligens as moch as I may <hi>veryt.</hi> I &amp; we deſyre you hartely to do ſo. <hi>vviſd.</hi> Sir it ſhalbe don. <hi>Knov.</hi> Brother veryte I haue no dought but that he ſhal take hyr tyght wel al though it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g firſt Wherfore I beſech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord be his ſpede. <hi>very.</hi> I men I pray y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> lord. <hi>vviſd.</hi> Mother meſſe I charg you i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the kinges name to delyuer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you your honor &amp; I tach you here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of heauens name, of tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſon theft &amp; murther. <hi>Meſſe.</hi> whi thou lurden, who made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo bold to tuch me, thy fingers ſhal rot of <hi>vuiſd.</hi> No no Mother meſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ld is not now as it hath ben, it is not your Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kerd doctrine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhal make me leue of houlde therfore be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, &amp; make nomore ado but
<pb facs="tcp:4680:7"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e your wais w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me, <hi>Meſſe</hi> Whi I pray you ſir what be you, and what is your name, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you haue a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> octorite to tach me, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I am not gilty i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. wiſdo, truly my na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me is wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, I am an officer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly king to ſerch out al wikednes. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe.</hi> Na the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue ſeruid a good ſeincte i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dede am I at this poynt now, I praye you maſter wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, who is my ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſers. <hi>vuyſd.</hi> Truly your accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers be thes veryte and knowleg me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a godli vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding <hi>Meſſe</hi> Verite &amp; knowleg. <hi>vuiſ.</hi> Yea truli <hi>Meſſe.</hi> Na the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mary I am like to ſuppe my porege i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> newgate, wel maſter wyſdome ſeing it is ſo as you haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what remedi but I wold deſier you this I knowe wel ſergantes be good felowes &amp; for monei wil do apleſur at a nede wherfore if you wil let me ſcape
<pb facs="tcp:4680:8"/>
now at this time I wil geue you for your ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlenes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> choyſe of thre thinges, <hi>Vuiſdo.</hi> what thinges be thoſe I pray you hartly <hi>Meſſ.</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry that be theſe, a biſſhopryk a be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefit or a C, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i. to dri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k, whether of theſe thre thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs ye wyl &amp; you ſhal haue for my ſuertes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal ſe you paid M, ſtifnec &amp; M. couetus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe be ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cial ye kno very wel &amp; I dar ſay they wyl not ſe me caſt awai for a lytle for they be my ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry fri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; ye may be ſur of this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> if theſe twayne cobbes ſtick vnto me ther is a greate ſorte moore in corners that wyll put to their por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> love me full well I thanke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherfore maſter wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeinge you haue ſuch ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſurties I truſt you wyll let me go, <hi>vuiſ,</hi> naye truly we depart not ſo as for theſe two parties I know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veri well they be not the men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wyll truſt
<pb facs="tcp:4680:8"/>
vnto nor non ſuch as they be but now I know who is your vphol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take hede or els they a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re lyke to knit the knot y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſhal knit. <hi>Meſ.</hi> by the maſſe I haue fyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed well now in dede why ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not theſe two honeſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> befor named bale me oute yf nede be. <hi>vuyſd</hi> no v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly no ſuch as they be but if ye bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g honeſt men to me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue god &amp; his word &amp; wilbe bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for your forth coming at al times I a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to let you go. els not, <hi>Meſ.</hi> nay then I am lyke to go in dede, wel M, ſergeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I wold deſyr you of charytie to let me go for Goddes ſake yf you wyll not let me go for none other mans ſake, <hi>vuiſdo.</hi> no no mother meſſe I know it is not Goddes wylle that I ſhoulde do eanye ſuche charitie. <hi>Meſſe.</hi> no is. <hi>wiſdome</hi> no vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye., <hi>Meſſe.</hi> Then doo wyth me
<pb facs="tcp:4680:9"/>
what ye will. <hi>vuiſd.</hi> come on youre wais you ſhall go with me, <hi>Meſſe.</hi> I am not very wel content. <hi>vuiſd</hi> what ſayſte thou. <hi>Meſſe.</hi> marye I ſay I am very wel content, <hi>vviſ</hi> antipus I do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand you in the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to lay this woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faſt in newgate that ſhe maye be forthe commi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to morow at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seſcione houſe. <hi>Antipus.</hi> ſir it ſhall be done with al my harte <hi>Vuiſd.</hi> loke that you do ſo &amp; make hir ſure. <hi>Antip.</hi> mother meſſe I am ſori of your tro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Meſſe.</hi> what remedi. <hi>Antip.</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly I can not tell, but yf I could I would but ſuch fare as I haue you be welcome to it ſo longe as you be here. <hi>Meſſe.</hi> ſir I thankyou hartely. <hi>vuiſd.</hi> Brother knowlege &amp; veryte you muſt be at the ſeſſcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> howſſe at .viii. of the clocke to mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row to put your inditment agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt mother meſſe. <hi>knouv.</hi> and I praye
<pb facs="tcp:4680:9"/>
you brother wyſdome haue you gotten hir. <hi>Vuiſd.</hi> I verely that I haue. <hi>Knouv,</hi> now the liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g god be praiſed, we wil not fayl by the gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of god, but we wil be there. <hi>gods Vuord the. luge.</hi> Inquere daniel if ther be eanye man that hath eanye matter to be intreated of this dai i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Seſſcione houſe let him bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it in. &amp; enter it &amp; he ſhalbe hearde. <hi>Dany</hi> yf there be any that hath ani matter in this ſeſcions houſe, let hym enter his accione for my lord iuge is ready to heare yt <hi>Iuge.</hi> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyell call forthe that woman ther <hi>Danye,</hi> mother meſſe ſtande forthe at the bare here. <hi>Meſſe</hi> here my lord <hi>Dany.</hi> hould vp your hande, <hi>Iuge.</hi> cal forth the queſt danyell. <hi>Dany:</hi> 0000 yes all them that be charged of the queaſte of mother meſſe my lorde commaunde you ſtraytly to apeare at youreical i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in payne
<pb facs="tcp:4680:10"/>
of hys hey dyſpleaſure 0000 yes, Simon Peter &amp; andrew come forth &amp; apere at your calling. <hi>Anſ,</hi> heare my lord, <hi>Dany.</hi> Iames zebede and Iohn his brother com forth &amp; apere at your calling. <hi>Anſ.</hi> heare my lord <hi>Dani.</hi> philip &amp; bartlemew co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth &amp; apeare at your calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. <hi>Anſ.</hi> heare my lord <hi>Dani.</hi> thomas &amp; mathew co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth &amp; apeare at your calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, <hi>Anſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> heare mi lorde <hi>Dany:</hi> Iames and thadeus com forth &amp; apere at your calling. <hi>Anſ</hi> heare my lord <hi>Danye,</hi> ſimo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of cane &amp; mathias come forth &amp; apere at your calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g <hi>Anſ</hi> heare mi lord. <hi>Dany.</hi> ſtand forth heare all xii and harkenne what ſhalbe layde to this womans charge. <hi>Peter</hi> whe wil my lorde. <hi>Iuge.</hi> Danyell make a crye to knowe whether heare be eany that haue eanye thing to lay to this womans charg ye or no <hi>Daniel.</hi> yf ther be eany ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hathe
<pb facs="tcp:4680:10"/>
eany thing to lay to this womans charge, let hym entir his matter for my lord Iuge is readito heare yt. know. my lord heare is a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath committed open treaſon theft and murder <hi>Iuge:</hi> howe ſayſt thou woman why anſweres not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> to thy complaint: <hi>Meſſe.</hi> my lord I do denye it, they are not able to proue it, nor no ſuch thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs as they laye vnto my charge. <hi>Veryte:</hi> &amp; it pleaſe you my lord that thing that my brother knowlege hath layde to hyr charge ys true and we are able to proue yt. <hi>Meſſe.</hi> Where in haue I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted this ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> treaſon theft and murder that you lai vnto my charge. I am ſhe that hath ben of a long continuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, inſtituted &amp; made by chriſt and his apoſtles &amp; aprouid by diuers, holy doctors &amp; for the ſpace af this, vi C. yeares I haue ben take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; halowed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:4680:11"/>
the cheafeſt as a woman mooſte neceſſarie for the peoples ſaluaty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and ſeing that I am ſprituall and Allowed by ſo many holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ordeyned by the holy ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and aproued by diuers ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doctors, my think my lord you ſhould not alow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> accuſations of theſe two men but puniſh them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other meughte take an enſample therby. know. my lord if it pleaſe you to heare my brother veritie &amp; I we wyl proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing true that we haue laid vnto her charge for wher as I ſayd that ſhe is a tray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour it is tru my lord by her owne wordes, for where as paule ſayth in the .x. to the Hebrewes that we are ſanctified by the offering vp of the bodye of Ieſu Chriſt ones for al, yet this blaſphemous mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter is readi dayly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her prieſtes miniſtring and oft times offreth
<pb facs="tcp:4680:11"/>
one maner of offerings which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer take away ſinnes but thys ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſu Chriſt the ſonne of god when he had offered for ſinnes. o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſacrifice which is of valew for euer ſate him downe on the right hand of God and from henſforth tarteth tyll his foes be made hys foteſtole for w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one offering hath he made parfect for euer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tified, &amp; thus we he taught in ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Paules doctrine therfore it is not for vs nor no other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur to beleue this wicked woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s doctrine for ſhe ſaith that ſhe can offer vp the body of Chriſt euery day to take away ſinne which is blaſpheme and treaſon for ſaint-Paule ſaith in the .vii. to the He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brewes that he dyd that ones for all when he offerred vp hym ſelfe wherbi bi hir doctri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſhe doth cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cify Chriſt euery day anew which
<pb facs="tcp:4680:12"/>
is to be knowne &amp; thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe is a vtter enime to god &amp; his word ye &amp; amore worſe traitor then whas Iudas which betraied chriſte, for Iudas whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had once betraied hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; delyuered hym in to the handes of his enymis, ſtrait way he knew he had done wyckedly &amp; through diſpaier he whente &amp; hanged hym ſelfe, but this traiterly woman ys not conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crucifieng him once or twyſe a day, or one day, but ſhe wil crucifi him v C. times eueridai in the yeare &amp; thinke yt al to litell &amp; not onely that but ſhe cauſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to beleue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cruel perſecuci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is neceſſary for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; thus I proue hir no leaſſe then a tretor, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth crucifi chriſt a new alſo athef which robith god of his honor, &amp; as for murderi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhe doth not onely ſle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hir damnable doctrine to go from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of our
<pb facs="tcp:4680:12"/>
ſaluation vnto her falſe doctrine to oure condempnacion but alſo all them that woulde not beleue it to be trewe and ſtycke to theyre opinion wyth cruell perſecutyon ſuffered deathe, As Rychard Hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, Roberte Kyng, Iohan Debin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham, Nycolas Marſhe, Thomas Sax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: Thomas Hitto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Thomas Bylney Richard Bifelde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Teu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſbery &amp; colyns. Willya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Leton george bainham Ihon frith Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bert Wulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tindale, Robert Barnes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gerard &amp; Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp; v C more y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe hath ſhed of innocent bloud &amp; by this <hi>I</hi> proue hir a trai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor: a thefe &amp; a murderer &amp; I a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re your lordſhyp wyll not ſay nay vnto it. <hi>Iug</hi> no truly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I will not if it be ſo: how ſaiſt thou woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it ſo ſpeade, <hi>Meſſe.</hi> my lord if it ple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe your lordſhip in dede I offer a ſacrifice for the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people
<pb facs="tcp:4680:13"/>
&amp; for al ſyknes diſeſes &amp; euil cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unſes and for faier wether &amp; rain which is chriſtes bodi &amp; blod but they can not ꝓue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, that I am neither traitor, thefe nor murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer for the ſcriptures beare me in that that I do. <hi>Knou,</hi> Why Eſai the prophet in his fyrſte chapter ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord doth abore youre Sacrifice euen at his very harte and wyl you compel hym to take it whether he wyl ye or no, and if he had delighted in ſacrifices as Dauid ſayeth in hys myſerere I woulde haue gyuen it the Lorde but thou delighteſte not in none ſacrifice lorde here Dauid decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth howe he hath no pleaſure in them which is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t inough to proue you falſe in that poi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and wher as you ſay that the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res beare you in it. I prai you in what place of ſcryptures do yow
<pb facs="tcp:4680:13"/>
bear your ſelf I could neuer rede that ther was any meſſe in Chriſt nor his Apoſtles time. <hi>Meſſe</hi> No what though the nam be not me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tioned in the Scriptures yet the thing it ſelfe is mentioned there for in me is Chriſt hym ſelfe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> form of bread and wine made by ſuch wordes as is taken out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripturs which chriſt lefte for vs, as in Mat .xxvi. Mar, xiiii. &amp; Lu .xxii. &amp; alſo as paul declareth in the .i. epiſtell to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cor .xi. chap wherin he ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord Ieſus the ſam night in which he was be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trayed toke bred and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked and brake &amp; ſaid take ye &amp; eat ye thys is mi bodi which is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you now then if Chriſt doth ſaye, this is my body will you ſai it is not his body. <hi>Veritie.</hi> no verely that I wyll not: but yet my lord ſhall rightly know both thou and thy
<pb facs="tcp:4680:14"/>
doctrine to be falſe ſuperſticion, for where as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaiſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of bread &amp; wyne after the wordes ſpoken taken out of, ſcripture which is as moch to ſai hoc eſt corpus meum this is my body truth it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſt ſaid this is my body but firſt you ſhal kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> when chriſte ſat among the twelue Apoſtles hauing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodi y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgin marye bare &amp; that ſame body y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgin mary bare, toke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his hand gaue thankes brake it &amp; gaue it to his diſciples nowe you ſhal know that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith that Ieſu chriſt becam in all poyntes lyke vnto man ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge ſynne, nowe I ricken that one mans body can be but in one place at one tyme, howe thynke you mother meſſe <hi>Meſſ.</hi> I mary y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is true a mans bodye can be but In one place at one time in dede
<pb facs="tcp:4680:14"/>
               <hi>verytie.</hi> Well then when the De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcyples had receyued the breade of the bodye that the Vyrgynne marye bare, where was that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye then, had they Eate it vp, or was it ſtyl preſente before them, <hi>Meſſe</hi> No theye had not eate it vp but it was ſtill preſent before them. <hi>Veriti.</hi> Well then That ſame bodye after it had Suffred death and roſe agayne yt aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp to heauen and let hym do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wne on the ryght hande of his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther &amp; there tarieth tyll his foes, be made hys fote ſtole, nowe that bodye is in heauen you wyll gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unt me thys. <hi>Meſſe.</hi> I verelye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is true. <hi>veryt.</hi> Howe chanſe it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that you wyll make the People beleue that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Subſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of bred and wyne is turned frome hys kynde vnto the verye Bodye of Chryſte that the Vyrgyn marye
<pb facs="tcp:4680:15"/>
hate after theſe woordes ſpoken, this ys my bodye, not that onelye but you make thereof a ſacryfyce for the remyſſyon of ſynne bothe for qwick &amp; dead which is great blaſpheme to the blode of chryſte &amp; they that woulde not ſo beleue ſholde ſuffer moſte cruell payne &amp; death, wher by ye haue crucified chriſt anew in his membres being no leaſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amourderer &amp; a there y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> robbeth god of his honor. <hi>Meſſe.</hi> why ſir god is omnipotent. <hi>Veryte</hi> I verely that is truth, <hi>Meſſe</hi> why then he may do all thinges &amp; ſeing he is almighty ſpeaki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des hoc eſt cor pusmeum, thys ys my body why ſhuld you then be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pugnant againſte the truthe, and ſaye that yt ys not hys Bodye, where as he ſaythe hym ſelfe that yt is hys bodye, and thys I am ſure of my Lorde that all them
<pb facs="tcp:4680:15"/>
that louithe me and he that ys in me, whiche ys god hym ſelfe, as I knowe there ys a greate meanye dothe, they wyll ſaye no leaſe but that I am ordeyned of God and that in ſeyng me, they ſe god hym ſelfe which mad them &amp; died vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe for them all, and if they receue me, they receiue their maker the body of chriſt fleaſhe blod and bone as yt hanged on the croſſe, and thus all them that fauerithe &amp; louithe me wilbeleue no leaſſe, <hi>Iug</hi> why I perceiue now thou haſt ſpoken againſte god &amp; hys worde hereſy and blaſpheme. <hi>Knouvlege.</hi> I truly my lorde ſhe word make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god of non effecte for by hir ſaying god dwelleth in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſton. yea &amp; ſhe techeth the peple to beleue no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lo <hi>Meſſe</hi> why my lord ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am made by god &amp; his apoſtles ordeined to be
<pb facs="tcp:4680:16"/>
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſaluatyon I thinke there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loueth me but wyll ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where as I am there is god for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripturs propheſied that meſſyas ſhould come which ſhould ſaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people &amp; I am ſhe, &amp; my abidyng is in Temples of ſtone whiche is gods te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple ſo well as mine, for lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke wher as I am ther is he. knou Why the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſamaria ꝓphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſied meſſias to be a he &amp; not a ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wher as ſhe ſaid, I wotwell meſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as ſhal com which is called chriſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is com, he ſhal tel vs alto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether here ſhe callyth hym a he &amp; not a ſhe meſſias &amp; where as you ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god dwellith in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples made of ſtone you ſhal know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. ſ. ſteuen ſaith that god dwelleth not in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> handes alſo, ſ. paule ſaith no leſſe to the xvii. af the ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god which made the worlde and all that are in it dwelleth not
<pb facs="tcp:4680:16"/>
in temples made with hande ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther is worſhiped with mens ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des as ſalomon ſaith in the thirde boke of the kings the vi, Chaptre that he builded him a houſe. how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit he that is hygheſte dwelleth not in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des as ſaith the Prophet Eſaye. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is my ſeate and the yearth is my foteſtoole what houſe wyll ye buylde for me ſayth the Lorde or what place is it that I ſhould reſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te in hath not my handes made al theſe thinges? now this blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous woman doth cauſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple to beleaue that he dwelleth in temples made wyth handes cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peple to take hir falſ gods for the lyning god wher as theſe honeſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth witnes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary which is ſuffitient inogh I truſt my lord to proue her falſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; whereas ſhe ſaith my lord y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he
<pb facs="tcp:4680:17"/>
that receyueth her after the conſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cration meaning the breade and wine two falſe goddes receaueth the body of Chriſt fleſh bloude &amp; bone, but after ſuch a faſhion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the Iewes the woorde of God in the. vi, of Iohan when he ſaid the breade that I wyll geue is my fleſhe whiche I wyll geue for the lyfe of the world now the Iewes toke it groſſly and ſtroue among them ſelues ſaying how can this fellowe gyue his fleaſh to eat, as doth thys woman theſe wordes of chriſte, this ys my bodye, takin the bare leter nothing conſideri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the cloſing vp ther of wher as he ſaith ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as you ſhal eat this breo &amp; drink of this cuppe it ſhal ſhew the lords death tyl he com &amp; if he be ther as this woman ſaith as I know he is not, let this nam ſacramente be cleane aboliſſhed
<pb facs="tcp:4680:17"/>
for he maketh yt but aſynification of the deathe of chriſt &amp; not chriſte hym ſelfe but rather you muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the Scripturs falſe which cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lithe yt a ſacramente or ells proue your ſelfe to be the Antechriſt that Chriſte byd vs beware of whiche ſholde exalt hym ſelfe in the ſeate wher the lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g god ſhold ſyt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is in mannes conſience &amp; theſe to be two falſe gods which you ſai ys the lyuing god, &amp; if the Scryp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turs be true you be atraitor a theſe &amp; a murderer, &amp; if they be not true a proue them your ſelfe. <hi>Meſſe.</hi> ſyr I can not denye but that the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turs be true. <hi>Iuge.</hi> then thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnyſt thy ſelfe a knowledgynge by thyn owne wordes to be giltye in that theſe two honeſte men do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay to thy charg. <hi>Peter.</hi> my Lord yf yt pleaſe you the accuſſacions of thes two men ys true, &amp; ſhe ys
<pb facs="tcp:4680:18"/>
gyltye in the thinge that they lay vnto hyr charge, wherfore my lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de yt ſhall not neade to panyell a queaſte of hir, for ſhe hathe conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned hir ſelfe, by hyr owne wordes, &amp; all we twelue breathern will gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unt ther vnto no leaſſe. <hi>Iuge.</hi> Why what thynke ye ys ſhe gyltye or vngyltye. <hi>Peter.</hi> gyltye my lorde, &amp; if yt pleaſe youre lordſhip or anye other man, to loke in the .vi. of ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruc the prophete you ſholde kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we wether ſhe or that, that ys i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be a god ye or no, <hi>Iuge.</hi> wel woman by the worde of god thou art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned vnto deathe for treaſon theft and murder, and ſeyng thou arte ſo thou ſhalte dye the deathe <hi>Stifnec</hi> my lord my brother coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. and I wold deſyre your lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſhyp that you wolde be ſo good as to let her go vnto the place fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wence ſhe came fyrſte. <hi>Iuge.</hi> no
<pb facs="tcp:4680:18"/>
that ſhe ſhall not for yt way cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that ſhe maye do moche harme in the weye as ſhe gotthe, <hi>Stifnec</hi> my lorde yf yt pleaſe you to ſet two ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt men to ouer ſe hyr my brother couetes and I wylbe glad to bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re there coſts what ſo euer yt be. <hi>Iuge.</hi> Well at your deſyer ſhe ſhal go, but ye ſhalbe bownde vnto me that you ſhall ſe hir convied ouer <hi>Stifnec.</hi> my Lorde that we wyll with all oure hartes, but we wold deſier your lordſhip that you wold be ſo good lorde as to leat hyr con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynu tyll the parlemente be paſte, and then wyll we ſe thie youre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente fullfylled. <hi>Iug,</hi> well I am contente that ſhe ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde wythe you till the perlement bedone, then vendicta dei and fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deſſperation ſhall haue the ouer ſeing of hyr to ſe hir convied to hir father the pope againe, and
<pb facs="tcp:4680:19"/>
for thy part vendicta dei, ſe thou that ſhe trauelith with moch pai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne and perſecucion &amp; let not my wrath neuer depart from hir but hang thou ſtill ouer hir heade for euer &amp; let hir neuer haue no proſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peryte but all ways in ſorowe &amp; care, and ſe that ſhe crepith not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to no mans houſe in eany wiſe as I knowe ſhe will, if thou take not good heade therefore wayte nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owlye vppon hyr and ſpecially a bowghte Powlles a monge hyr fryndes there, and Ludgate and ſayncte pulckers, and ſe that ſhe carieth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hyr, hir two brother ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perſticyon and Idolatry, and for thy parte fynall deſperacyon, ſo that ſhe be broughte to hyr Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys end wyth owght Soker or comfort and that ſhe neuer retur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne agayne wiles the world indu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth but alwayes to abide In vn
<pb facs="tcp:4680:19"/>
comfortable paine as a thing deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perate of all comfort neuer to ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne mercy. <hi>final,</hi> My lorde ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicta dei and I ſhal ſe this youre commaundement fulfylled vnto the vttermoſte. <hi>Iuge.</hi> I pray yow hartely do ſo &amp; take hir w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you.</p>
            <p>NOw gentle audience where as I haue wyth iuſte cauſe condempned this mounſter by gods word perceyuing no leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe then that ſhe is the abho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of deſolacion and the greate babilon the mother of whoordo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and hath ſet her ſelfe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te where god ſhould ſyt as ſaint Iohn ſaith in his reuelacyon the xvii. Chaptre the waters ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angell vnto ſaynt Iohn which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaweſte, where the whore ſytteth are people and folke &amp; nacions &amp; though and in that ſeat ſhoulde the lyuynge god ſit, whych ys in
<pb facs="tcp:4680:20"/>
mens conſcience and I perſeiue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe hath taken the honor vnto hir ſelfe, whyche ſholde be due onelye vnto the lorde I can do no leaſſe of conſcience but: Iuge hir a thefe whyche robithe god of hys honor not onely this coulde ſatiſfye hyr wycked deſier, but ſhe hath cauſſed the people wythe hyr doctryne to beleaue that ſhe was the lyuynge god, and a mediator betwixte the rather of heauen and them to paci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye his wrathe, where as ſayncte paule ſaithe in the ix, to the hebru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that yt is chryſte that pacifieth hys fathers wrathe and not that he ys entred in to holy places that are made wythe handes which ar but ſimilituds of tru things but he is entred into very heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere now i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of god for vs not ſo offere hym ſelfe often as thys woman dothe, making the people to beleue that ſhe offerith him vp
<pb facs="tcp:4680:20"/>
euery day a ſacrifis for the quick and the dead to take awaie ſinne wher as ſainct paule ſaith in the vii. To the hebrues that he ded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> once for al whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he offerid vp him ſelfe, and in the .ix. Chaptre folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge ſaith ſaincte Paule wyth ought ſhedi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of blode ther is no remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinn by the whiche by hir doctrine, ſhe crucifyeth chryſt euery day a new, and not onely in hir doctrin but alſo ſhe ꝑſecuteth him a freſh in hys faithful mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers if they wold not beleaue hir falſe doctrin, &amp; tak hir to be their god by the whiche ſhe is a tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor &amp; murderer &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is left vnto vs for a memorial of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ath of chriſte and a worthy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente of the bodye and blode of Ieſu Chriſt ſhe ſayth it is god hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf the bread and wyne I meane two falſe goodes cauſynge the
<pb facs="tcp:4680:21"/>
people to do homage &amp; worſhip vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them, wher as chriſt bad them eate it and drink yt, and not to wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip yt to make ther of a god. I co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ulde bryng In dyuers pointes of Scripture to proue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſe gods and playne Idolatrye to worſhip them, but I differre yt vnto the neaxt tyme, deſyringe all chriſten men to beware of thys wycked ſprite for ſhe is the roſſe coloread whore that ſainct Iohn ſpake of In hys reuylacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the xvii. chap which is ful of blaſpheme, that the kings &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habiters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth haue dronke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wine of hir fornicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but feare not ſaythe ſayncte Iohn in his ii, Chapter for ye ſhall haue tribulacion and thys wycked ſprit the deuyll ſhall caſte you in to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone but be faithfull ſaith chryſte vnto the deathe and I wyll gyue you a crowne of euerlaſtinge lyfe
<pb facs="tcp:4680:21"/>
whiche lyfe ſhall endure for euer be feruent therfore my Bretheren and repent ſaythe ſaint Iohan in the third of his reuelacion be hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſayth Chriſt I ſtond at the do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and knocked if anye man heare my voyce and open the doore. I wyll come in vnto hym and wyll ſuppe wyth hym and he wyth me and ſeinge he hathe lyke a mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full father promiſed vs this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull promyſe, let vs therfore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente and be feruente to open the dore oure hartes I meane which is locked vp in vnbeleue that he may enter in and there is no dout then but that he wyll ſuppe wyth vs and we with him vnto the which ſupper I beſeche the lord brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vs all vnto, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:4680:22"/>
            <head>YOw ſubictes of baal ſay what ye wil kick ſpurn &amp; wiſe, as moch as you mai make as manye Goddes as you can it ſhall not ſkyll yt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lenth with owt dowght you ſhal what your playe.</head>
            <p>A trewe prouerbe, &amp; ſpoken may it be.</p>
            <p>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the falſe ſuttle antechriſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r meſſe.</p>
            <p>The nyer the Churche the furder from God.</p>
            <p>(quod). W. P.</p>
            <p>A fawt eſcaped in the firſte leafe the fyrſte page euerye tree Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe the .vi. Reade Mathewe vii</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4680:22"/>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4680:23"/>
            <head>ImPrYnted</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON BY VVYLLY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> Hyll, And Wyllaym Seres. Dwelling in Paules Church yeard At the ſigne of the grene Hyll<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>ANNO. M. D. XLVIII.</hi> The .xvii. day of decembre. <hi>Cum Gratia et Priuilegio ad Imprimendum ſolum</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4680:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
